Guide to the Order of Red Friars records, 1913-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Order of Red Friars records 1913-1971.
Duke University. Order of Red Friars.
2 linear feet
Duke University. University Archives
Contains the records of the Order of Red Friars, a senior men's secret honorary society, founded in 1913 at Trinity College (now Duke University). Types of materials include minutes, a constitution, policy and procedure statements, history statement, rituals, correspondence, financial records, invitations, photographs, membership and alumni lists and cards, newspaper clippings, reports, stationery, initiation plans, and descriptions of projects. There is one artifact, a "Featherweight Pocket Seal" (with accompanying leather case) which bears the Red Friars' seal. Major subjects include secret societies, honorary societies, student life at Duke University, male students, student government, initiation, social activities of students, the honor code, student participation in Duke University administration, and student activities during World War II. Some people associated with the Order of Red Friars include Rex Adams, Arthur Hollis Edens, Herbert J. Herring, Furman McLarty, Raymond Nasher, Richard M. Nixon, and William H. Wannamaker. Materials date from 1913 to 1971. English.
uaredfriars
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
Transfer; 1970; 70-243
Unknown source; 1975; 70-243
Unknown source; 1980; 70-243
Gift; 1985; 85-131
Unknown source; 1987; 87-12
Unknown source; 1994; 70-243
Gift; 1997; A97-74
Historical Note
The Order of Red Friars was a secret men's honorary founded in 1913 by members of the senior class at Trinity College (now Duke University). The Red Friars' mission was to promote social spirit at Trinity College; later groups declared their purpose was to foster loyalty and interest in the university through anonymous service in student organizations. Officers consisted of Grand Friar (President), Worthy Friar (Vice President), Grand Recorder (of minutes), Grand Treasurer (Treasurer), Grand Communicator (conducted correspondence), Grand Keeper of the Gate (guarded door at meetings), and Grand Herald (notified members of meetings).
Each year's group consisted of seven men, the Septemvirate, chosen by the previous year's leaders, based on their character, scholarship, qualities and potential of leadership, and outstanding service to the university. Tapping ceremonies were held in late spring, and grew more elaborate over the years. In its final and most traditional form, a red hooded figure publicly tapped new men to membership on the steps of Duke Chapel. This ceremony, the wearing of red carnations once a month, and the ringing of "Charley" the Friars' bell, were the only public notices given to the organization. All activities and projects were kept secret. Two projects conducted completely by Friars were the creation of the plaque of Duke University's aims and the plans for the construction on West Campus of a Red Friars' monastery.
Members of Red Friars held leadership positions in Omicron Delta Kappa, Young Men's Christian Association, Inter-Fraternity Council, the Judicial Board, Freshman Advisory Council, Men's Student Government Association, Associated Student Government of Duke University, class offices, athletics, the Chanticleer, the Chronicle, the Men's Glee Club, and fraternities. Members had been involved in student government and social activities since their arrival on campus, and by their senior year, became part of this special group of leaders on campus.
Achievements of Red Friars were aimed at improvement of student life and the development of loyalty to the university. Because the Friars were also leaders of student government and social life, many ideas conceived in Friars' secret meetings later were brought to life without the campus being aware of their origins. Other schemes not conceived of by Friars were successful because of the motivation of support by Friars in their various positions of campus leadership. Examples of both are the Wartime Student Activities Board, Joe College Weekends, reorganization of fraternity and rush rules, agitation for change in the housing system, course and professor evaluations, elimination of Duke and Duchess, improvement of student-faculty relationships, and pep rally planning.
The Friars were very important to the President and Deans of the university both as a means of discovering and influencing student opinion; they were often were privy to information that was not widely known on campus. These relationships were reinforced by the fact that many faculty, administrators, and Board of Trustees members were Friars or had been given an honorary membership. The Friars had up to three honorary members at any given time, composed of upper level administration and faculty members. Honorary members included William Preston Few, William H. Wannamaker, Robert L. Flowers, James Cannon, George Allen, Herbert Herring, James Truesdale, Coach Wallace Wade, Everett Weatherspoon, Alan Manchester, Furman McLarty, Ted Minah, Arthur Hollis Edens, William Griffith, Thomas Southgate, Marshall Pickens, and Raymond Nasher. The Friars held meetings with members of the faculty and administration to discuss campus situations and plans for action. Opinions of both university and student leaders on issues such as wartime regulations, integration, drinking rules, fraternity regulation, housing problems, and the honor system are contained within these discussions.
The Friars suspended its activities during World War II due to constant fluctuation in the student body that made it difficult to choose students who would be in attendance for a full school year. Friars' activities were suspended at the close of the 1942-1943 school year and an alumni committee formed to reestablish the order post-war. The Friars were restored with the graduating class of 1949.
Red Friars voluntarily disbanded in 1971, after failing to tap new members in 1970. Throughout the 1960s, the order increasingly faced charges of elitism and had difficulty selecting members who would accept membership. In 1971, after a meeting of Friar alumni, the order was discontinued as it was considered to have outlived its usefulness for the university and the student body.
Although the order has never been reestablished at Duke University, Order of Red Friars alumni continue to provide exceptional leadership and support of Duke University endeavors.
Collection Overview
Contains the records of the Order of Red Friars, a senior men's secret honorary society at Duke University, founded in 1913. Constitutions, policies, correspondence, tapping ceremony materials, and minutes outline the influential activities of the Red Friars from about 1913-1971. Materials are ordered by subject; some gaps occur between 1943 and 1948 due to World War II. An index of members is also included.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Adams, Rex, 1927-; Duke University. Order of Red Friars; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Presidents; Duke University -- Societies, etc; Duke University -- Student housing.; Duke University -- Students -- Social life and customs; Duke University -- Students -- Societies and clubs -- Honor societies; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Edens, Arthur Hollis, 1901-1968; Few, William Preston, 1867-1940; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Nasher, Raymond; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-; Secret societies -- Rituals; Secret societies -- North Carolina -- Durham; Student participation in administration; Wannamaker, William H.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943, 1949, 1956, 1964, 1967, 1969-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Related to Initiation Banquets, 1952-1958 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Related to Initiation Banquets, 1959-1965 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Related to Initiation Banquets, 1966-1970, undated (Folder 4)
  - Financial Records, 1938-1943, 1949-1958, 1962-1964 (Folder 5)
  - Financial Records, 1939-1943, 1949-1953, 1959, 1965-1969 (Folder 6)
  - History of "Charley" the Red Friars Bell, 1927, 1951, 1953 (Folder 7)
  - Instructions to New Septemvirate, 1959, 1969, undated (Folder 8)
  - Membership Lists, 1913-1943, 1949-1956, 1958 (Folder 9)
  - Membership Lists, 1913, 1915-1943, 1949-1950, 1968, undated (Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1965, 1969, undated (Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1913, 1953-1955, 1959, 1960, 1970-1971 (Folder 12)
  - Notes from Initiation Banquet, Spring 1961 (Folder 13)
  - Opening Ceremony for Meetings, undated (Folder 14)
  - Photographs, Tapping Ceremony, 1953 (Folder 15)
  - Program for Red Friars Ladies' Night, May 20, 1925 (Folder 16)
  - Project, Red Friar Monastery, 1936-1937, undated, photographs (Folder 17)
  - Project, Plaque of the Aims of Duke University, 1942 (Folder 18)
  - Project, Bus Boycott, 1949-1950 (Folder 19)
  - Project, House System, 1959, 1967 (Folder 20)
  - Project, "Student's Guide to the Duke Faculty," 1964 (Folder 21)
  - Project, "Report of the University Center Committee to the Educational Facilities Committee," 1964-1966 (Folder 22)
  - Project, Proposed Shield, undated (Folder 23)
  - Reference materials and notes, Minutes of Duke University Religious Council, April 23, 1959 (Folder 24)
  - Reference materials and notes, "Constitution of the Men's Interfraternity Council," April 1960 (Folder 25)
  - Reference materials and notes (Folder 26)
  - Men's Student Government Association Dormitory Evaluation Commission, "Alternative Living Arrangements Available to Sophomores," January 5, 1963
  - Reference materials and notes, "Your Student Government," 1964-1965 (Folder 27)
  - Reference, Wall Street Journal clipping, November 11, 1968 (Folder 28)
  - Stationery, undated (Folder 29)
  - Tapping and Initiation Ceremonies, 1916, 1966, 1967, 1970, undated (Folder 30)
  - "Featherweight Pocket Seal" and leather case, undated (Folder 31)
  - Constitution and Minutes, Volume One, 1913-1931, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Minutes, Volume Two, 1935-1943, 1949-1950 (Folder 33)
  - Minutes, Volume Three, 1951-1954 (Folder 34)
  - Minutes, Volume Four, 1955-1960 (Folder 35)
  - Membership cards, 1913-1943, 1949-1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
Related Material
Duke University. Office of the President records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Order of the White Duchy records.
University Archives, Duke University.